Mss.Rec.83 Mss.Rec.83
American Philosophical Society
Pima Bajo materials
1970
Mss.Rec.83
American Philosophical Society
17.0 Reel(s)
This collection includes word lists, history, and texts (some with translation). Informants were Pedro Estrella Tánori and María Córdova, both of Onabas, Sonora, Mexico.
17 sound tape reels (15 hr., 53 min.)
Cornell, John R.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by John R. Cornell and accessioned, 1971 (Acc. 1971 855r). This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Biographical/Historical note
John R. Cornell, the recipient of an American Philosophical Society Phillips Fund grant, created the collection.
Indians of Mexico--Languages; Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Pima Bajo language; Pima Indians; Sonora (Mexico: State)--Languages; Sound recordings; Vocabularies.
- Audio recordings
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-07; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:30; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-07; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:54; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-07; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:51; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-08; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:47; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-08; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:25; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-10; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:37; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word lists, 1970-08-11; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:09; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word lists, 1970-08-12; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:45; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo text, 1970-08-12; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:40; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Scope and Contents note
    Story told in Pima Bajo from 8:20 to 12:55 preceded and followed by conversation in Spanish.
    Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language; Pima dance; Pima Indians--Social life and customs
  - Pima Bajo text, 1970-08-12; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:44; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Three short accounts told in Pima Bajo, with conversation in Spanish.
    Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language; Pima dance; Pima Indians--Social life and customs; Yaqui Indians
  - Pima Bajo text, 1970-08-15; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:41; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    In Pima Bajo only.
    Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language; Pima Indians
  - Pima Bajo text, 1970-08-17; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:19; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Two short accounts told in Pima Bajo, with Spanish conversation.
  - Pima Bajo text, 1970-08-20; 05-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:39; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Corn--Mexico; Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language; Pima Indians--Food; Pima Indians--Social life and customs
  - History of consultant, 1970-08-13; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:33; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Interview regarding consultant's background and family structure, conducted in Spanish only.
    Family histories; Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Indians
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-14; 06-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:59; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word list and interview, 1970-08-14; 06-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:26; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Pima Bajo word elicitation up through approximately 15:00, followed by an interview on the current Pima Indian population.
    Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language; Pima Indians
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-15; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:34; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-17; 07-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:01; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-19; 07-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:15; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word list and history, 1970-08-25; 07-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:08; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Brief word list, followed by interview on the current Pima Indian population. Predominantly in Spanish.
  - Pima Bajo grammar, 1970-08-17; 08-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:45; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language--Grammar
  - Pima Bajo grammar, 1970-08-21; 08-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:56; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo text & translation, 1970-08-18; 09-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:26; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Through 13:47, transcription of a previously recorded Pima Bajo text as it is played back in short units. From 13:47, translation of text into Spanish.
    Fuelwood gatherers; Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language; Pima Indians
  - Pima Bajo text & translation, 1970-08-19; 09-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:28:10; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Transcription of a previously recorded Pima Bajo text as it is played back in short units. From 24:21, commentary by consultant in Spanish only.
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-18; 10-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:21; Cornell, John R.; Córdova, María
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-20; 10-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:58; Cornell, John R.; Córdova, María
  - Pima Bajo text & translation, 1970-08-20; 11-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:23; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Transcription of a previously recorded Pima Bajo text as it is played back in short units, with occasional explanation in Spanish. From 13:15, commentary by consultant in Spanish only.
    Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language; Pima Indians; Yaqui Indians
  - Pima Bajo text & translation, 1970-08-21; 11-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:46; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Translation into Spanish of a previously recorded Pima Bajo text as it is played back in short units.
  - Pima Bajo text & translation, 1970-08-21; 11-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:43; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Transcription of a previously recorded Pima Bajo text as it is played back in short units, with occasional explanation in Spanish.
    Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language; Pima Indians--Social life and customs
  - Pima Bajo grammar, 1970-08-21; 12-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:21:29; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-21; 13-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:48; Cornell, John R.; Córdova, María
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-22; 13-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:53; Cornell, John R.; Córdova, María
  - Pima Bajo text & translation, 1970-08-24; 14-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:43; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo text & translation, 1970-08-25; 14-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:38; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo text & translation, 1970-08-26; 14-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:44; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo text & translation, 1970-08-26; 14-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:37; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Coyote; Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language; Pima Indians
  - Pima Bajo grammar, 1970-08-24; 15-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:05; Cornell, John R.; Córdova, María
  - Pima Bajo grammar, 1970-08-25; 15-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:51; Cornell, John R.; Córdova, María
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-26; 16-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:18; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
  - Pima Bajo texts and conversation, 1970-08-26; 16-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:22:41; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Two accounts given in Pima Bajo, from beginning through 1:36, and 16:17 to 17:58, with commentary and conversation in Spanish.
    Indians of Mexico--Sonora (State); Onavas (Sonora, Mexico); Pima Bajo language; Pima Indians--Social life and customs; Yaqui Indians
  - Pima Bajo text & translation, 1970-08-27; 16-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:54; Cornell, John R.; Tánori, Pedro Estrella
    Through 22:30, transcription of a previously recorded Pima Bajo text as it is played back in short units. From 22:30, translation of text into Spanish.
  - Pima Bajo word list, 1970-08-26; 17-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:24:07; Cornell, John R.; Córdova, María